Hello.
Great.
Where are you from?   The
city of Pskov.
Oh, city of Pskov paratroopers.
Ah, yes, that's the one.   Are
you a paratrooper?   Yes.
No, it didn't work.
Failed.  Why not get it?  They didn't
take it.
Well, I study at university.
How old are you?
19.
Cool.  I thought you were about thirty years old by now
.
Well, maybe he grew one right under his nose
.  It was worth about thirty.
Understood.  And what do you communicate with,
nineteen-year-old?
Well, about all sorts of things.
In general, I come to practice languages.
Which?
Well, what kind?  English and German
first.
Why do you need English and German if
you live in Pskov?
Well, then, in order to
continue
working in other areas that
require
knowledge of the language.
What direction is this?
Well, the direction of the region of responsibility is at
least international relations.   Yes.
Understood.  Interesting.  Listen, since
you're interested in international
relations, listen, what's
happening between Russia and Europe right now?
Nothing good.  at least.
Well, there is a war going on between Russia and
Europe or not?   There is
no direct war with Europe.
Okay, let's do it this way.  Who is Russia at war with?
With Ukraine.
So it turns out that Russia has not been able to
defeat Ukraine for so many years.   Yes.
I wonder
why?
The unpreparedness of
the troops, even from the very beginning of 2022,
was explained to
Comrade Supreme Commander-in-Chief of the
Federal Security Services regarding the
readiness of, firstly,
Ukrainian combat units to fight back, and
specifically, this, what can we
call this compass, well, roughly speaking, the
consent of the Ukrainian people to the actions in
Russia,
that they will be greeted with flowers.  Yes,
yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes.
Got it, got it.  Interesting, yes.  OK then.
Well, in 1922, well,
they saw, yes, that they wouldn’t be greeted with flowers
, everything somehow fell apart there, yes.
Why hasn't anything changed?   It's
already the twenty-second year, the twenty-sixth
year, yes, the middle is passing.
Well, let's say it was in September, there was a
mobilization in September,
yes, they mobilized these people and realized
that, well, it's not worth
mobilizing anymore, because otherwise, at the very
least, there will be angry wives, mothers and mothers of
their children, and politically it's
not at all advantageous.
Therefore, the resource is quite limited and
mobilization-based.
They lured me with money as best they could.  At
this stage, well,
the people who would go
there for millions of billions of suitcases of
dollars for a hypothetical Chinese
SUV are practically finished.
And,
firstly, human resources are simply
limited due to
self-limitations.  There has
not yet been a total mobilization and there will not be one.
Secondly, well, there's corruption in the Ministry of Defense,
that our money isn't spent on fortifications
, nor on the development of this
unmanned drone industry, that
, well, I heard something like this somewhere, that
one commander tells another, that
we're bringing a truckload of
drones to the front for a truckload of your supposedly mobilized troops.
That's it.   Do
n't know.  a lot regarding the Russian military-industrial complex
, because, well, I never
follow it, I know what successes Ukraine
is achieving in this regard.   Yes.
Well, in any case, an offensive
war requires more resources
than,
say, defense, if you
will. Yeah.
And if the fortification is really good,
then it’s just grinding the
edges, the edges.  front
resources troops.
Yes, good.  What about Russia?  Well, it's already been
going on, 4 years of the Second World War have passed, yes, it's
already been going on longer than the Great
Patriotic War, yes, it
will soon be longer than the Second World War.  And
the question is, how does Russia see how to win
this war?
And the Ministry of Defense, or at least Putin
himself, they live in slightly different worlds
than the population.  That is,
how there are these flag-stickings
at the front, which help to build a
picture of widespread seizures and
advances on all fronts.
These people
take out loans, as they say, for some
conventional settlements.  That is,
nothing has been taken yet, but there is a plan.  So
, guys, send them there in
small assault groups.  And it
seems to me that no one here is
interested in victory because of the civilian population.  In any case, I have not
heard, either in person or in absentia, about any
desire for victory.
Perhaps in 1922
such feelings were still relevant, as if,
well, there
was still some confidence in the military
capabilities of one’s own state,
that this is still possible, and this is what we need,
and this is what we need.
And then suddenly, that's it.
Okay, well, okay.  Well, how is it, anyway?
Because Ukraine, with the help of the West, is
simply increasing its long-
range shelling of Russian territory every month.
I, uh, wake up in the morning, I don’t
even have time before. I was just getting coffee and looking,
oh, they hit there, they hit there, somewhere
, and now there are so
many attacks on Russia in one night that I
don’t even have time to look through and
understand everything that happened there while I’m having coffee.  And this
will continue to increase.  How does Russia
plan to counter this?   How should
I know?   I do
n't have any positive expectations on
this matter.   Yes.
And in your place, for example, do you have
some kind of alley with photographs of those who died there
?
Mm, I'm not sure.  I know about local
monuments located in the villages there
.  Here in my place
of birth there is a small alley somewhere
near the stadium.  That is, it is not a
very busy place.  Where there is an alley,
there is a cemetery right next to it.   I'm
just curious.  Here in Ukraine,
in every city, yes, uh, in the city center,
either in the square or on the central
pedestrian street, yes, there is an alley with
photographs of everyone.  And here in my city of
Khmelnitsky, if I walk along the
central pedestrian street, there are
cubes with each large photograph, yes, a
caption, where he died, on
what date, who he served, yes, and here is
each one, yes, that is, we do not hide
these people, yes, but show that they
defended the homeland, yes, and here they are, yes, there are
many of them who died, but here they are.  But
for some reason, in Russian cities, yes,
they hide from the population their people, who are
supposedly heroes, supposedly defending the homeland.
Why is that?
Because it is not politically advantageous to
show the
actual number of victims.
Well, yes, it’s also kind of unprofitable
to show it in Ukraine, but Ukraine shows it.
Ukraine shows that it is a hero.
Because, well, because these are
heroes for Ukraine, and that’s how it is for us.
Either mobilized soldiers who were simply
unlucky enough to be mobilized,
or contract soldiers.
Understood.   There are
very few ideological ones.  There, conditionally,
DShRGruch, these guys.  Do you,
for example, have any acquaintances in Pskov, or
even outside of Pskov, or any acquaintances at all,
who have already died or been wounded?
No.  No, thank God.
And which ones fight at all?
No.
Understood.  It's just interesting.  You probably
don't have a clue, but you've been communicating
with this category of
people for 19 years, right?  Well, yes, it's
interesting.  And for example, I remember
in 1922, in all the cities, and
in Pskov too, people hung Z-marks on their
cars.  Everything was so wonderful for
them, right?  And now the Z-girls
were getting late from their cars somewhere.  Somehow they don’t really
care anymore that they support the
war.  Is there such a thing?  Yes.
Well, yes, it’s like anyway, here
or there you’ll still find a conditional Z-connector
on the rear window of a car, but this is
rare, yes.  And in principle, since the beginning of the war, it
seems to me, they have not been so often, at
least in my region.  I don't know
how it is in others.
Interesting, huh?  As you see, uh, how
will these things develop further
, how will these events develop in Russian, yes,
for you, as a Russian.
And here, according to what scenario will the
conflict end, if it does, if I
catch it?
Well, in any case, we can only hope for the
best, but, as I see it, for now we are pinning our hopes
on the upcoming
State Duma elections, which, perhaps, will change something
and, perhaps, the people will somehow
express themselves, at least once will
show their discontent en masse, in any case, at
least with the election results.
Well, what about the election results if
only the right people are allowed to vote?
Well
, I don’t know, they haven’t let everyone in yet
, they haven’t let everyone in, they haven’t let everyone in.
I know about the Yabloko party and follow their
actions.
How about in St. Petersburg, someone simply
lost their business, like these guys.   They are
fabricating cases against someone for
demonstrating these Nazi symbols and so
on.
Understood.  Interesting.
But the mood in Russia
now is that people want it to stop
somehow, or they say it will last until the
bitter end.  Well, what's the
general mood?  Because there are
no victorious endings before.  That's for sure.
What's the mood?
Well, their mood is more connected
with the current problems that we
face ourselves as citizens.  This is the
gasoline restriction, there is an increase in the prices of
goods taking into account the increase in the prices of logistics,
since gasoline is also not so
affordable.
Mm,
basically, I don’t know how
people feel about this.  I
communicate, well, more like left-wing
liberals, like my group at the
university at least.   Yes.
And like,
yeah, I have a pretty narrow
opinion.
Well, okay, but for example, from the
political spectrum, who are left-wing liberals
in Russia?
Precisely from official representatives.
Well, yes, well, there is nothing
closer to the apple.
Well, Apple, are they really left-wing liberals?  It
seemed to me that they were not right-wing liberals.   Yes.
No, more
European orientation would be enough.
No, well, I mean the left there - that's
socialism and all that stuff.
Well, definitely liberals, in any case, I
never tried to get into this political topic.  Well, for
example, uh, I don’t see, yes, how in
modern Russia it’s even legal for
some opposition
forces to come to power by the elections, yes, because, well, uh, in
reality, they’re not allowed to participate in these elections either in that
same Yabloko in St. Petersburg or in
Moscow somewhere.
And in many cities, yes, they
simply did it this way. If somewhere else, from
Yabloko, for example, in Irkutsk, or wherever there was a
guy activist, everything, but they found out about him, that
means that in some year he
had a post on VKontakte with an
Instagram icon, and Instagram is now
banned in Russia, they issued him
some kind of fine and supposedly banned him from
running because of it, right?
They do it like that, right?
So, in general, do
you believe that elections can
change anything?
The elections themselves are not directly related, but at least
some message has been
delivered: let the same party have an apple.
That is, there are adequate people
in the country, that at least don’t lose
this hope.
Well, yes, I just think that when the
elections are over, yes, they are essentially just around the
corner, they are in September, if I'm not
mistaken, the elections,
yes, from the 18th to the 20th. So essentially, there are
two months left, yes, two months, even a little less than
two months left until the elections,
yes, it will already be clear, yes, that, let's say, the
elections will not change anything and, most likely,
mobilization will be announced after the elections, because I see that
preparations for mobilization are
being made.
In 1922, the same thing was done
after the presidential elections: they immediately announced
mobilization before the elections, so as not to
confuse the people.  And now
preparations are underway, the military registration and enlistment offices have been given
access to legislative data, yes, and all sorts of other things,
in short, there are other things that
show that systematic
preparations for this mobilization are underway, right?
How can Russia respond to this
mobilization?  People will simply obediently go
again, like in twenty-two.
But I don’t know what can
actually be expected in this regard.
In any case, there was already experience of mobilization
.
However, now they are tightening the
screws more in terms of movement within
certain countries.  So, just now there
was some news about a
law being signed that gives
the Ministry of Defense access to data,
for example, for the Aksa Unified Register,
they are planning to
issue permission to leave the
country.  Well, well
, yes, an exit visa, yes, you have it.   Yes.
Well, it’s like they used to say it was a hoax,
but it’s quite
believable, in any case.   It’s just that
, as it seems to me, what will be the
difference between the mobilization of
26th year and
22nd year.  In '22, people were still there,
well, many panicked, and they started to
leave Russia right away.  That same
Verkhniy Lars was stormed, yes, a lot of people
left, but many went on these
summonses, because there was a feeling that
now, well, in a
month or two, like, and now we are mobilized,
now it will all end, yes.  Uh, I
think that over these four years, all of Russian
society has seen where all those
mobilized soldiers have gone. Yes, they've simply
dissolved, yes, in this stream of war, and
essentially, there are none left. Yes, everyone sees
how, over these four years of war, more and
more coffins are arriving to friends, relatives, and
so on. Yes, that before, Russia was there,
it was pressing its power, and now Kherson has already, uh,
fled from Kherson.  Then they fled from the
Kharkiv region.  Now Ukraine is
already taking out all these Walberries,
oil refineries, and bombarding
all those fleeing the meat assault on the front with drones
.  Everyone can see this.  That is, it
seems to me that in 26 the
mobilization will not be so smooth.   There
might be some pretty serious riots.   Do
you believe that there could be riots in Russia
or don’t you believe it?
Well, there will be riots for sure.  Just on what
global level?  This is such a
question,
because
Ai,
if they do, then, most likely, there is a very
high chance that there will be
no more mobilizations and
something will change within the country.
Well, we can only hope for that
, because, well, nothing is
known.   I can't make any
predictions.
So it turns out that
the only hope for Russians is that something will somehow
resolve itself.  That's how it
works, right?
Well, not by itself, but so that there would be a
reason, so that
some reason would happen, so that everyone would rise up
for their own safety, at least for the
sake of it.
Understood.
And is it true that I saw many
bloggers making videos about how shopping
centers are closing down, there are tons of costs,
rent, rent, rent,
stores are closing, and so on, yes, because of the
economic crisis.
How is this in your shopping centers in Pskov?
I don’t know, I don’t go to shopping
centers.   You have
n't seen it, have you?  That is to say, it is
interesting.  But do you have, for example,
acquaintances who have somehow
changed their position over time, for example, they used to be
against war, but now, on the contrary, they are for
war.  Or, on the contrary, they were for war, but
now they are against war.  Or they weren't
interested in politics there, but now because of
all this shelling they're somehow interested.
The war began, I was 16 years old.  Then I
studied at school.  At school, I
mostly had
classmates who liked to drink
and, well, someone there because of my
environment.  But it’s not that we were strongly in favor of the war
, but we
weren’t even fiercely against it.  In
any case, this is just the
basic era, let's say.  And
over time, I simply changed
my social circles, that is, I graduated from school,
entered university,
and new people formed.  As for the old ones,
I don’t seem to maintain contact with many of them
simply because communication didn’t
work out before.  It's just
not interesting.  Well,
as far as I can remember, no one has ever
changed their opinion, at least.
Understood.  Well, that is to say, so unnoticeably, right?   Yes.
For example, on the streets of your
city, are there any marches,
on the contrary, for support of the war, for
ethnic groups, or is there nothing like that anymore?  There were no
motor rallies there.
No, car rallies only
happen during national holidays.
There was Navy Day on May 9th recently.
Today is Navy Day
.  Or am I not yesterday?  Yesterday, the twenty-
sixth, I think.
Yes, yesterday.  Yesterday, the twenty-sixth.
Well, I'll take a look now.  Yes,
Airborne Forces.  It seems to be there since August 9th.
No, I'm on August 2nd.
Yes, I don’t remember anymore, I don’t understand
it.
So, July 26th, yes, yesterday.  Yes.
Well, I
get it.
Oh, by the way,
yesterday, yes, they
posted a video on Navy Day, Putin was hosting
some kind of parade, yes, against the backdrop of a
painted submarine, that is, they were holding it
somewhere, not even on the shore of some sea
.  Have you seen it or not?
No, I haven't seen it.
Understood.  And how do people feel about the fact that
the majority of the ruling cliques in Russia, say, are
people in their 70s, like those Lavrovs and
others?  Putin and so on, yes, they are
65-70
plus years old.
Well, it’s not that
most people do, they probably just don’t
ask any questions.  Just a familiar
routine, let's say.   It's
just that now, it seems, the majority of
the population is living in a completely new
reality, yes, there are smartphones, the Internet,
some kind of freedom of enterprise,
yes, and these old men, like, well, they are dragging
this whole gang down, as it seems to me.
There is no such feeling.   It's
not that I know much, in
principle, about their activities.  They do not
shine except with their heads and
their sayings.  And it seems to me that they
certainly don’t have the final say,
in any case.
Understood.
They gathered there, well, the grandfather with the other
grandfathers will be more comfortable than the hammer.
Yes, than with the youth.
I agree to go there.  Yes.  Do you have any
questions?
Well, I don't really have any questions.
Understood.  And how are things in Russia now, for example,
with gasoline?  Here they showed us that there
were huge queues.  Are these fakes or are these
queues?  Yes, at first.  Now
this whole thing has resolved itself, in my opinion, the
restrictions are not as strong as they were.
That is, in principle, this excitement has died down,
yes, as it were,
right?
Well, I get it.  But in Pskov there wasn’t one,
you don’t have an oil refinery,
that’s why there wasn’t one there.
No, and there never was.  Yes, we are not just
transit to St. Petersburg.
Understood.  That is, in principle, it affects you,
that is, how much they bring, yes, time.
I wonder if you have any concerns?
Yes, maybe, I don’t know, because at the
top they say that NATO wants to take over
Russia and so on.  Do you have
any concerns, yes, among you, among
your circle, among the people in Pskov, that
NATO will invade the Pskov region?   What kind of
poverty is this in Latvia in Estonia?  Well,
if suddenly, my God, NATO decides
to transfer troops to the Baltics,
it will be, I don’t know, conditionally to protect
the border from this side, Kaliningrad,
there, Belarus, coming back and forth, that there will
be such a ring.  This is
not strategic at all.
Well, it’s just that
all Russian propaganda is
nationalistic, that NATO wants to take over
Russia, take over, take over, NATO is
advancing there, and so on.  How do you
even see NATO attacking
Russia and why?
Oh, NATO, NATO.
Well, that's what was said about Putin's chances
of invading Estonia and Latvia,
so conditionally.
speech protinarians, Latgalian people's
republics and so on.
Conventionally, NATO would most likely not
immediately intervene on their behalf.
But if there is a direct threat to
existence,
then yes.
I wonder how to determine whether there is a threat to
Russia’s existence or not?  Like,
well, a threat to NATO's existence.
Ah, NATO.  Got it, huh?  So, in your opinion,
if Russia had invaded, for example, the
city of Daugo, taken over Latvia, that is,
Latgale, yes, and NATO would have kept silent
and nothing would have happened, right?
No, well, if they hadn’t kept silent, that would, of course, have
caused panic, at least in the
bordering countries again.  And
there I don’t know how much about because
NATO,
well, at the moment is much more
disunited than it ever was before.
with the isolationist directions of
Donald Trump, also the main
beneficiary of the entire alliance.
But now, as a result of the
NATO Joint Forces Command, NATO has expanded and
Finland and Sweden have joined, right?  That means
NATO is already right next to St. Petersburg,
and right next to the northern part of Russia.
How do people in Russia feel about this and do
they watch anything?  Are there any worries
?
Yes, I think very few people
remember this.
That is, well, we joined NATO and we joined, right?
Well, yes.  Like,
why do so many people say that
Ukraine can’t be in NATO?
Who the hell knows, because that's what
they said.
Understood.
Okay, thanks for talking.  Victory
further.   Well, yes
.
19 years old, such a mustache.  That's all
their greatness.  Yes, they don’t know anything about what to
do or how to do it.  They are already
apathetic, and this is good for us.  But in the autumn of
26 it seems to me that
Russia will carry out mobilization.  And here it will be
very important to
raise awareness of this topic in
Russia, so that there will be unrest, so that
there will be some kind of, uh, let's say, not
rallies, yes, but riots and so on, yes,
like there was in Dagestan in twenty-
two.  And now, yes, now everyone who
sends their husband or son to Russia for mobilization
will understand
that this is a one-way ticket.  In twenty-
second they thought this now, it’s for a couple of
months.  Like, subscribe, comment.
Subscribe to our WhatsApp channel, here is the
QR code.  There, news
similar to that in the Telegram channel is posted
for those who don’t have Telegram or who don’t
use it for other reasons.
Subscribe to our WhatsApp channel.